Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. We are definitely nearing the end here
and today's דף Daf is קנ"ד. Kuf Nun Dalet. We pick up
at the bottom of קנ"ג Kuf Nun Gimmel and we're talking about
this issue about if somebody finds themselves as it's getting dark outside
of the city with their wallet, how do they get back home?
I did want to say, Shua, Michael's not here because he's always
interested in the הלכה Halacha aspect of it, but I did double-check
some of the issues that came up. First thing I should say
is the last גמרא Gemara we ended up with is that the
גמרא Gemara wants to know that, you know, that if in the
advice that you should just run home and not stop and therefore
you'll remember and you won't stop in the street, well what happens
when you get to your house? So it says you drop it
כלאחר יד Kil’achar Yad in your house. So I said the גמרא,
Gemara, the reason the גמרא Gemara didn't ask that question by putting
it on the animal is because then there was like, there was
never an עקירה. Akira. You put it on the animal, if the
animal was moving, you don't have to worry so much about the
הנחה. Hanacha. But תוספות Tosafot asks, well what about the case about
when you're walking פחות פחות מארבע אמות? Pachos pachos me’arba amos? That's
the same issue. You can go,
you can traverse רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim with פחות פחות, Pachos pachos,
but at a certain point you're going to leave רשות הרבים Reshus
Harabim and go into רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid, right? And you know,
so how do you deal with that? Of course you could say
you stop in a כרמלית Karmelis and from the כרמלית Karmelis you
go to your house, so it's only דרבנן. Derabanan. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot
says yeah, could, you know, should have asked the same question there
and presumably it would be the same answer that you drop it
כלאחר יד. Kil’achar Yad. Now the other, I think, very relevant question
was the issue of חוץ לתחום. Chutz L’techum. Let's say you're outside
of the תחום. Techum. And here, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and
the רמ"א Rama פוסקין Pasken interestingly that, you know, because as we
already saw, they didn't מתיר Matir every דרבנן. Derabanan. They allowed, for
example, you to put it on a, on an animal, but they
did not allow you to put it on, to on your friend
and have, you know, as your friend was moving. רש"י Rashi actually
says that that case, I mean, it's I, you know, it's relatively
obvious, but anyway, that case is the case of שנים שעשוהו. Shnayim
she’asu’u. I pick it up, it's almost like the first משנה Mishnah
about the עני Ani and the בעל הבית. Baal Habayis. I pick
it up and put on my friend as he's moving and that
they didn't allow. So, you know, again, Michael asked yesterday what if
two people carry it together? Well, at least a certain version of
שנים שעשוהו Shnayim she’asu’u they don't allow. So they didn't allow everything.
You know, they tried to sort of define exactly what yes, what
not. מוקצה Muktzeh they did allow as we said, but that because
clearly, you know, the wallet and מוקצה Muktzeh and so on and
you're picking it up and putting it down, you know, as the
animal's moving. But anyway, but as far as the תחום Techum issue
is concerned, the רמ"א Rama basically פוסק Paskens that, if you're afraid
for סכנה Sakana issues, like that you don't, you know, get into
the city, you're going to be endangering yourself, then you can obviously
violate תחום Techum concerns because you're out there in the middle of
nowhere and who knows who, you know, what type of bad people
are around. But if it's not a סכנה Sakana concern, you cannot,
you cannot violate תחום. Techum. So it's interesting, you know, they were
concerned that you would actually violate carrying on שבת Shabbos and they
do all these tricks by carrying, but somehow if there's also a
תחום Techum concern, then they said no you have to stay where
you are. So at least that's the way the רמ"א Rama rules
about it.
He can move at all?
Well, you can move as far as your תחום Techum goes, you
know, but if my תחום Techum ends, you know, 3000 feet outside
the city, I have to stop 3000 feet outside the city.
But I'm 3000, I'm outside of that.
I'm outside the city, I started 5000 feet outside the city. Right.
I go 2000 feet and then I stop. And then I can't
continue unless there's a סכנה Sakana concern. That's at least the way
the רמ"א Rama rules about that. So, yes.
What about when these rabbinic prohibitions take effect at all?
For בין השמשות?
Bein Hashmashot? Okay, so that's true. There's a position certainly about רבי
Rebbi that there's, that the דרבנן Derabanans don't apply בין השמשות Bein
Hashmashot certainly במקום מצוה. Bemakom Mitzvah. So that would be certainly an
issue as well.
What's the status of תחום? Techum? Is it דרבנן Derabanan or דאורייתא?
De’oraisa?
תחום, Techum, well, we פוסקין Pasken it's דרבנן, Derabanan, but there is
a position of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that it's דאורייתא. De’oraisa. But
we פוסקין Pasken it's דרבנן, Derabanan, so it's not based on thinking
it's דאורייתא. De’oraisa. It's just one of these things that sometimes there's
these arbitrary, you know, distinctions about this yes, this not, and it's
not exactly clear, you know, exactly, exactly why. Okay, so let's keep
on continuing in the גמרא. Gemara. I should, one last final point
I want to mention is this issue about putting it on a
minor. There's a debate of רמב"ם Rambam and תוספות Tosafot whether even
when you put it on the minor, you know, that scenario, it
also had to be only as the minor was walking, similar to
the donkey case. Because it's interesting, and this is actually as a
good segue into beginning today's דף, Daf, the donkey case of all
of these was a דאורייתא De’oraisa concern. Of having your donkey do
work for you on שבת Shabbos and leading your donkey and so
on. If it's not your kid, it's not a דאורייתא De’oraisa concern.
So actually, right? Because it's, you know, you're, you're commanded regarding your
kid's resting, not somebody else's kid. So this issue about picking it
up as the donkey, you know, wait till the donkey moves then
put it on and after the donkey stops pick it up, wait
till it moves again and so on, according to the רמב"ם, Rambam,
that only applies by donkey, does not apply by minors, because you're
not commanded if it's not your kid on making sure that your
minor rests.
Whoa, that's revolutionary! Where do you see anything like that, that you're
not responsible for somebody else's performance? Well, somebody else is responsible for
his...
Well, because it's not like a חינוך מצוה. chinuch mitzvah. The מצוה
mitzvah is, meaning there is a חינוך chinuch issue here, you know,
and that becomes, so that's an issue like the מגיד משנה Maggid
Mishneh explains the רמבם Rambam says okay, you know, but חינוך chinuch
means well not חינוך chinuch because again חינוך chinuch is on the
parents but you're not supposed to make a קטן katan do a
sin. But he says you know,
מצוה, mitzvah, you know, yeah, okay, yeah.
So right,
you're responsible that your child should...
am I responsible to make sure... let's not talk about child, let's
talk about animals. Am I if your animal is
somebody is plowing with your animal am I responsible to make sure
it stops plowing?
Whose animal is it?
Your animal. Am I responsible to stop your animal from plowing on
שבת? Shabbos?
Well, that's a different question than are you allowed to have it
do מלאכה melacha in the first place.
No, because the whole idea here is each person is commanded to
make sure all of the parts of his household are resting: his
kids, his animals, his slaves. So it's not that the it's not
like the concern is for the kid doing the עבירה. aveirah. The
concern is is that members of your household are doing מלאכה, melacha,
you know. So therefore that's your concern, that's not my concern. But
you're saying you're saying that I'm being מכשיל machshil you in the
שביתה shvita of your kid. I see your point. Okay, that's an
interesting point. You're saying that I'm making you עובר oveir because... but
but I would say by the way, ah okay, but here that's
a good point if I'm making you be עובר oveir inadvertently even
if you're unaware I'm causing you to be עובר oveir on the
שביתה shvita of your kid. But I would say also that the
שביתה shvita of your kid is specifically when your kid generally speaking
when your kid is doing מלאכה melacha for your sake. When he's
doing מלאכה melacha for somebody else or for himself that's not included.
So there could be a way that you avoid the problem altogether
not just that it's not my kid. Well, you know, because it's
not my kid then it's not even defined as שביתה shvita because
he's doing it for somebody else. But I hear the point. Anyway,
I did want to mention that that it could be that the
case of the animal is worse than the case of the kid,
that's the way the רמבן Ramban understands it. And that's a good
segue, let's continue begin officially today's דף daf with a discussion about
the animal. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, five lines down
in wide
lines. אמר רבי בר חמא: Amar Rabi Bar Chama: המחמר אחר בהמה
בשבת, Hamachmer achar behemah beShabbos, בשוגג חייב חטאת. beshogeg chayav chatas. If
somebody actually is מחמר machmer from the word חמור chamor which means
that you basically are moving your donkey along. I think it says
אחר achar because you lead a horse and you follow a donkey,
is that right? No? Anybody know? Anybody ever work travel with donkeys?
Okay, anyway, so what?
I just think it's true that they use a switch on donkeys,
right?
Right, right. Okay, so there you go. So anyway, if somebody anyway
leads his donkey with the load on שבת, Shabbat, then בשוגג חייב
חטאת מזיד חייב סקילה. beshogeg chayav chatas meizid chayav sekilah. So according
to this position it's ממש mamash a מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbos,
you
bring a קרבן korban if you do it בשוגג beshogeg and you're
חייב סקילה chayav sekilah stoning if you do it במזיד.
bemeizid. It's like any of the other לט מלאכות, Lamed Tes Melachos,
using your animal to do מלאכה. melacha. Now I should mention here
I'll stop for a second and point out that the פוסקים poskim
actually develop the point that there are two different types of, I
mean it's actually in the ראשונים Rishonim or whatever but anyway, two
different types of issues around your animals. One is like your kids,
you know, which is the מצוה mitzvah of שביתה. shvita. למען ינוח
שורך וחמורך, Lemaan yanuach shorecha vachamorecha, you know, ensure that they rest.
So so there that's a מצות עשה, mitzvot asei, ensure that your
donkey rests. And that's even if you're not participating in the activity,
you're just like if I rent my animal out to a non-Jew
and he works my horse or my donkey I am transgressing שביתת
בהמתו. shvitat behemto. But that's only my animal, I'm not transgressing if
I if I work with your animal I'm not עובר oveir שביתת
בהמתו. shvitat behemto. That's again the members of my household but that's
even irrespective of whether I'm involved as long as I'm allowing it
to be worked on שבת. Shabbat. That's the מצוה, mitzvah, the positive
מצוה mitzvah of למען ינוח. lemaan yanuach. There's a negative prohibition which
is לא תעשה כל מלאכה אתה ובנך ובתך lo taaseh kol melacha
atah uvincha uvitiecha etc. וחמורך, vechamorecha, you have ושורך וחמורך. vashorecha vachamorecha.
So there that's understood to actually be not about a negative prohibition
but it's when I am actually working directly with the donkey, אתה
וחמורך atah vechamorecha when you are taking and using your donkey to
do מלאכה. melacha. So when that's the case, not just it's doing
מלאכה melacha but you're using it and it's in the same פסוק
pasuk of לא תעשה כל מלאכה lo taaseh kol melacha according to
one opinion that ממש mamash is חילול שבת chilul Shabbos and חייב
סקילה chayav sekilah at the highest level. Okay so that's the first
position. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
דאמר קרא deamar kra the פסוק pasuk says לא תעשה כל מלאכה
אתה ובהמתך. Lo taaseh kol melacha atah uvehemtecha. So the same פסוק
pasuk of you not doing work which is the חייב סקילה chayav
sekilah פסוק, pasuk, the you know full חילול שבת chilul Shabbos it
says you and your animal. בהמתך דומיא דידך, Behemtecha dumya dideich, your
animal is just like you. מה הוא בשוגג חייב חטאת במזיד חייב
סקילה אף בהמתך נמי בשוגג חייב חטאת במזיד חייב סקילה. mah hu
beshogeg chayav chatas bemeizid chayav sekilah af behemtecha nami beshogeg chayav chatas
bemeizid chayav sekilah. Same way you get a חטאת chatas or סקילה
sekilah when you do it with your animal as well. By the
way רשי Rashi also says that אתה ובהמתך atah uvehemtecha specifically connects
to the מלאכה melacha of
leading. It's as
if you did the מלאכה melacha all by yourself and you're
חייב סקילה. chayav skila. Okay, but what's supposed to have happened if
the
donkey decides, I'm gonna go carry it by myself?
Or let's say, I don't know, let's say you put your donkey,
you put some food out there and your donkey is walking after
the food but you're not directly involved as it's walking and as
it's carrying. You could have set the whole scenario up, but if
you're not directly involved then, as it's doing the מלאכה, melacha, that
is not at certain -- that is not the suggestion that you're
חייב סקילה chayav skila and it might not even be מחמר. mechamer.
מחמר mechamer is a case when which is the לאו, lav, again
not just the עשה aseh of שביתת בהמתו, shevisas behemto, and it
could be a case where you are very like highly involved in
the process, participated, I should say, not involved, participating in the process.
A couple of years ago I actually asked a שאלה shaila about
our cats cutting toilet paper on שבת. Shabbat.
And not only is there not prohibited -- do I not have
to try to stop them, I can even use the cut toilet
paper. There you go. They were doing it on their
own.
Right. Okay.
Does this same thing apply for like your עבד? eved?
So right, that's a good question which I don't want to get
into, but I alluded to before about how you understand קטנים, katanim,
how do you understand עבדים, avadim, to what degree. The גמרא Gemara
assumes, the short answer is that the גמרא Gemara assumes that the
מצוה mitzvah of שביתה, shevisah, like the -- like allowing them to
rest, the מצות עשה mitzvas aseh is by minors and slaves. It's
specifically by animals that the גמרא Gemara thinks that there's a possibility
that it's ממש mamash a real מלאכה melacha because you are using
it as you are doing the מלאכה. melacha. So that's actually considered
as you're doing the מלאכה, melacha, at least that's the possibility, you're
doing the מלאכה melacha with it and that's seen as a לא
תעשה. lo taaseh. Yes.
What if you have a service animal that they work as a
seeing eye dog? Aha.
Yeah, but that's not a מלאכה. melacha. So again, the problem --
well, isn't that their מלאכה?
melacha? Yeah, but it's not one of those thirty-nine מלאכות melachos of
שבת Shabbos which is how this is defined. Okay, so the רמב״ן
Ramban says by the way, there are cases where we won't פסקן
pasken this way by מחמר, mechamer, but there are cases he says
where you would be חייב סקילה. chayav skila. Let's say your cow
is plowing and the רמב״ן Ramban says you're actually holding onto the
plow and helping sort of guide the plow as the cow is
moving it. So you're not actually pulling it, but you actually are
directly holding onto the plow and the cow's pulling it. According to
the רמב״ן, Ramban, that actually would be as you did the מלאכה.
melacha. But here it's you're not, its doing it but you're involved.
But I want to go back to seeing eye dogs. They have
to wear -- they have to wear a heavy thing when they're
working. They have to wear this harness. Right. So that would be
a מלאכה, melacha, right? They're carrying.
Unless you define it as a מלבוש, malbush, and that was a
whole פרק perek that we had about the -- about what's a
-- yeah,
it's not really a --
okay, but those are the discussions. I understand. But you had things
that were health-related that were defined as not a burden, so that
would be the way to go there. That's how those things are
addressed. Okay, let's continue here. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
So that's the logic here. It's like ממש mamash you did it.
At least that's what רבא Rava said because now רבא Rava is
going to respond. So he says you're חייב מיתה. chayav mita. אמר
רבא שתי תשובות לדבר. Amar Rava: Shtei tshuvos ladavar. I've got two
answers, responses. חדא דכתיב תורה אחת יהיה לכם לעושה בשגגה והנפש אשר
תעשה ביד רמה. Chada dichtiv: Torah achat yiyeh lachem leoseh bishgaga vehanefesh
asher taaseh beyad rama. So this is, there's one rule for those
that do in error and then if you did willfully, etc. This
is about עבודה זרה avoda zara but it's also about bringing a
חטאת. chatas. הוקשה כל התורה כולה לעבודה זרה. Huksha kol hatorah kula
leavoda zara.
Everything is connected to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. מה עבודה זרה דעביד
מעשה בגופו, Ma avoda zara deavid maaseh begufo, עבודה זרה avoda zara
is only when you actually physically do an act. הכא נמי דעביד
מעשה בגופו. Hacha nami deavid maaseh begufo. Here only also when you
do physically an act. Number one. Number two: ועוד תנן המחלל את
השבת בדבר שחייבין על שגגתו חטאת ועל זדונו סקילה. Veod tnan: Hamchalel
es haShabbos bedavar shechayavin al shigagaso chatas veal zdonos skila.
If somebody violates שבת Shabbos for something that when you do it
in error you bring a חטאת chatas and when you do it
intentionally you get סקילה. skila. מכלל דאיכא מידי, Michlal deika midi,
so it says that type of
חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, then you get סקילה, skila, etc. So that
suggests that there's another form of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos that doesn't
have a חטאת chatas and doesn't have a סקילה. skila. Well what
type of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos doesn't have a חטאת, chatas, doesn't
have a סקילה? skila? מכלל דאיכא מידי דלא חייב על שגגתו חטאת
ולא על זדונו
סקילה. Michlal deika midi delo chayav al shigagaso chatas velo al zdonos
skila. So there's got to be something it tells us like that
is a form of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos without that. And what
would that be? לאו דמחמר, Lav demchamer,
the prohibition of leading, of working your donkey. So גמרא Gemara says,
so you see, you can infer from that that it is a
חילול שבת chilul Shabbos but not of the same category. And says,
not necessarily, לא, lo, maybe not. תחומים אליבא דרבי עקיבא והבערה אליבא
דרבי יוסי. Techumim aliba deRabbi Akiva vaavara aliba deRabbi Yosi.
There are two other versions of חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says תחומים techumim are דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, we don't פסקן pasken
by him but again, it's a, אל יצא איש ממקומו ביום השביעי,
al yetze ish mimkomo beyom hashevi'i,
but it's not a חילול שבת chilul Shabbos of the highest level.
You don't get חייב מיתה chayav misa but it's a לאו lav
that applies on שבת. Shabbos. And according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi,
the fact in this week's פרשה, parsha, right? It says לא תבערו
אש בכל מושבותיכם ביום השבת. lo siva'aru eish bechol moshvoseichem beyom haShabbos.
Although it's the one מלאכה melacha that's singled out, he says רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says it's singled out to tell you you don't
get מיתה mita for it, you don't get סקילה skila for it.
It's a לאו, lav, it's a prohibition but it's not of the
highest order. So there's possible opinions of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos without
חייב מיתה. chayav misa. סקילה, skila, you don't, maybe, and maybe מחמר
mechamer still is חייב סקילה. chayyav skila. So here you have this
very, you know, radical idea that it would be ממש mamash as
if you're doing it with the donkey and that you would be
חייב סקילה. chayyav skila. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't end that way.
Let's continue. דף קנ"ד עמוד א'. daf kuf-nun-daled amud aleph. רב זביד
Rav Zevid מתני
הכי, masni hachi, רב זביד Rav Zevid teaches it the following way.
אמר רמי בר חמא, Amar Rami bar Chama, המחמר אחר בהמה בשבת
ham'chamer achar behema b'shabbat בשוגג bishogeg אינו חייב חטאת, eino chayyav chattat,
but במזיד b'meizid חייב סקילה. chayyav skila. Well, okay, that doesn't help
so much. So he says, okay, you won't be חטאת chattat בשוגג
bishogeg maybe because a חטאת chattat has these ideas of having to
do an action and you didn't directly do the action, but at
least you would get סקילה skila if you did it במזיד b'meizid
because sometimes we have doing that, you know, like somebody
who is מגדף megadef or something, you would have cases where you
don't do a full action, you know, a full physical action and
you're חייב סקילה. chayyav skila. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מתיב רבא, Masiv Rava, רבא Rava
asked this. One minute, but we teach, המחלל שבת בדבר שחייבין על
שגגתו חטאת, ham'chalel shabbat b'davar she'chayyavin al shigagaso chattat,
if you violate שבת Shabbat something that you bring a חטאת, chattat,
then חייבין על זדונו סקילה. chayyavin al z'dono skila. So anything that
you bring a חטאת chattat for, you get סקילה skila for. So
that implies, says רבא, Rava, הא אין חייבין על שגגתו חטאת, ha
ein chayyavin al shigagaso chattat,
that implies that if there's no חטאת, chattat, אין חייבין על זדונו
סקילה, ein chayyavin al z'dono skila, then there's no סקילה. skila. It
says, if there's a חטאת, chattat, there's סקילה, skila, means if there's
not חטאת, chattat, there's not סקילה. skila. Now anybody ever take elementary
logic? If P then Q, does that mean if not P then
not Q? No. No. It means if not Q then not P.
Right? If P then Q, right? If it rains, we're not going
to the ballgame, or that's where I, I don't know, if it's
sunny, we're going to the ballgame. So it could mean that if
it rains we're also going to the ballgame, I don't know, I'll
decide when if it rains, but we're super-duper certainly going if it's
sunny. If P then Q doesn't mean if not P then not
Q, okay? So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, מי קתני הא אין חייבין? mi kasni ha ein
chayyavin? It didn't
say if there's no חטאת, chattat, there's no סקילה. skila. הכי קאמר,
hachi ka'amar, דבר שחייבין על שגגתו חטאת, davar she'chayyavin al shigagaso chattat,
חייבין על זדונו סקילה. chayyavin al z'dono skila. If there's a חטאת
chattat then there's definitely סקילה. skila. ויש דבר v'yesh davar that there's
not חטאת, chattat, go either way, ויש דבר שאין חייבין על שגגתו
חטאת v'yesh davar she'ein chayyavin al shigagaso chattat וחייבין על זדונו סקילה,
v'chayyavin al z'dono skila, and maybe you would get סקילה. skila. So
if there's חטאת, chattat, there's definitely סקילה. skila. If there's no חטאת,
chattat, maybe yes, maybe no. Okay. ומני מחמר? u-man hi mechamer? It
could be מחמר. mechamer.
So it is possible here that מחמר mechamer is, this is very
strange, it's technically basically this position agrees with pretty much with the
previous one, it's ממש mamash full חילול שבת, chilul shabbat,
but maybe for a technicality because you're going to get סקילה, skila,
it's gotta be full חילול שבת, chilul shabbat, but you're not going
to bring the קרבן korban because there are maybe more requirements for
a קרבן korban and there you didn't physically do the action yourself.
Okay. רבא Rava אחוה דרב מרי בר רחל, achua d'Rav Mari bar
Rachel, רבא Rava
the brother of רב מרי בר רחל. Rav Mari bar Rachel. Now,
why is he called בר רחל, bar Rachel, why is he called
by his mother's name, not his father? Because based on another גמרא,
Gemara, his father was a גר. ger. So he was actually attributed
to his mother, I mean what's the matter about father being a
גר, ger, but anyway the גמרא Gemara chose to attribute him, there's
some interesting discussions about his father, his father's name was איסור גיורא,
Issur Giyora, איסור Issur the גר. ger. Now here, the next couple
of lines in the גמרא, Gemara, רש"י Rashi tells us, תוספות Tosafot
says is clearly wrong and you just see from the language we're
going to read, it clearly is a later gloss that was stuck
into the גמרא. Gemara. But we'll read it because it's interesting. ואמרי
לה, v'amri lei, some people say, before we even get to what
he's saying, some people say that רבא Rava wasn't the brother of
רב מרי בר רחל, Rav Mari bar Rachel, I mean it's not
the same רבא. Rava. Normal רבא Rava would just say רבא. Rava.
So we're not talking, so this רבא Rava that we're talking about
wasn't the brother of רב מרי בר רחל, Rav Mari bar Rachel,
but אבוה דרב מרי בר רחל, avua d'Rav Mari bar Rachel, he
was the father of רב מרי בר רחל. Rav Mari bar Rachel.
And then this and then it goes on to say, לישנא בתרא
lishna basra but according to this idea that he was the father,
קשיא הא דרב kashya ha d'Rav אכשריה לרב מרי בר רחל achsharieh
l'Rav Mari bar Rachel ומניה בפורסי דבבל. u-manieh b'fursi d'Vavel. The סוגיא
sugya that we have
a difficulty from the סוגיא ביבמות. sugya b'Yevamos. The סוגיא ביבמות sugya
b'Yevamos says that רב Rav appointed רב מרי בר רחל Rav Mari
bar Rachel a type of an officer in בבל, Bavel, and that's
a whole discussion about whether a convert can hold certain positions of
authority. And the you know, and the גמרא Gemara discusses that, you
know, whether he can or he can't, and why רב Rav did
it and so on, and basically the answer is because his mother
was Jewish even though his father was a גר. ger. So anyway,
this is saying, ah, so you see from that גמרא Gemara over
there that his father wasn't רבא, Rava, his father was a גר.
ger. That גמרא Gemara makes it clear that that was the whole
problem and that was the whole discussion. Okay, so again clearly this
is a later gloss. This is not the גמרא Gemara sort of
you know saying, you know, say, oh, but based on that סוגיא
sugya this doesn't make sense.
Anyway רבא Rava was a
גר, ger, I don't understand.
What? Maybe this רבא Rava was a גר. ger. Yes, so תוספות
Tosafot sort of says, you know, then it would have been רבא
גיורא Rava Giyora or something, who knows, but it's a good point.
רבא Rava the father of רב Rav the son of רבא. Rava.
What?
Yeah, and it's not it's not the standard רבא Rava anyway. Okay,
anyway moving on.
Why did they give him acknowledge that he's the father and then
to say the father of so and so the son of the
mother? That's what I'm saying. That's like, right, that he's not the
father.
Right, why would it say the father of right, why would it
just say, I know, the whole thing is strange, which is why
רש"י ותוספות... Rashi v'Tosafos... cut the whole thing out; they say it's
clearly wrong, it's some gloss. Anyway, moving on. Okay, so here's what
he said: עסקינן לא להשמעתא משמיה דרבי יוחנן לפטור. Askinan lo lehashmeita
mishmeih deRabbi Yochanan liftur. He teaches the same discussion as a מימריה
memreih דרבי יוחנן deRabbi Yochanan but to say that you're exempt, that
you don't get סקילה skilah or חטאת. chatas. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar
Rabbi Yochanan says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan מחמר אחר בהמתו בשבת פטור
מכלום. mechamer achar behemto beShabbos patur miklum. If you did this you
are fully exempt, meaning you don't get a punishment. Okay, it didn't
mean that what you did wasn't a biblical violation, but you don't
get a punishment. בשוגג לא מחייב חטאת. Beshogeg lo mechayev chatas. In
בשוגג beshogeg you don't bring a חטאת chatas as we said before
דהוקשה כל התורה כולה לעבודה זרה. dehuksha kol haTorah kullah l’avodah zarah.
It's all linked to עבודה זרה avodah zarah for the purpose of
a חטאת. chatas. חטאת Chatas requires an action, no action, no חטאת,
chatas, which is why there was a position before that said no
חטאת chatas but yes מיתה, misah, but now we're going to say
you also don't get מיתה. misah. במזיד נמי לא מחייב מיתה. Bemeizid
nami lo mechayev misah. Also for במזיד bemeizid you don't get מיתה.
misah. דתנן Detnan because we have a משנה. mishnah. המחלל את השבת
בדבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת Hamichalel es haShabbos bedavar
shechayavin al zedono kares veal shegagato chatas like we said before, if
you violate שבת Shabbos with something that you do a חטאת chatas
and סקילה. skilah. And he makes sort of the same similar inference
which we said is not necessarily a proof. האין חייבין על זדונו
כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת אין חייבין על זדונו סקילה. Ha’ein chayavin al
zedono kares veal shegagato chatas ein chayavin al zedono skilah. If there's
no חטאת chatas then there is not going to be סקילה. skilah.
Okay, so you don't get סקילה. skilah. Now how about getting lashes?
You transgress the biblical prohibition of לא תעשה כל מלאכה אתה ובהמתך.
lo sa’aseh kol melachah atah uvehemtecha. So it says בלאו נמי לא
מחייב. Belav nami lo mechayev. You also don't get a לאו lav
דהוי ליה לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין. dehavah leih lav shenitan
leazharas misas beis din. Because that לאו, lav, לא תעשה כל מלאכה
lo sa’aseh kol melachah is the same prohibition for doing the action
that you get executed by the court for doing a willful חילול
שבת. chilul Shabbos. And there's a general principle like that you can't,
if you use the לאו lav for one purpose you can't use
it for another, that you only get a punishment if there's a
biblical verse that is sort of by itself prohibiting that act. So
once the verse of לא תעשה מלאכה lo sa’aseh melachah is being
used for a more important purpose to basically tell people that if
you violate this verse you get מיתה misah if you do real
חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, you can't use that same prohibition for a
more minor infraction and to say that you get lashes. Now normally
the assumption is it doesn't mean that you haven't transgressed this prohibition.
Yes you've transgressed it but we can't use it to be the
basis of giving you a punishment because it's there to serve a
larger punishment. Okay, so this huge תוספות Tosafot is just trying to
figure out the parameters of when we say that it's already being
used for the execution punishment and can't be used for something else.
Okay, so he says בלאו נמי לא מחייב דהוי ליה לאו שניתן
לאזהרת מיתת בית דין. Belav nami lo mechayev dehavah leih lav shenitan
leazharas misas beis din. It's a לאו lav that is given for
the sake of warning you against something that is a capital crime.
וכל לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין, Vechol lav shenitan leazharas misas
beis din, any לאו lav that is given for that purpose, okay,
אין לוקין עליו, ein lokin alav, you do not get lashes. So
there's no מלקות. malkus. So maybe you've transgressed this לאו lav but
there's no מלקות. malkus. And then the גמרא Gemara goes on top
of קנ"ד עמוד ב'. kuf nun daled amud beis. This is why
we were able to have a little discussion at the beginning of
the שיעור shiur right back. So the גמרא Gemara says ואפילו למאן
דאמר לוקין. Veafilu leman deamar lokin. Even according to the approach that
you do get lashes for this type of a לאו, lav, here
you won't. ליכתוב רחמנא לא תעשה כל מלאכה ובהמתך. Lichtov rachamana lo
sa’aseh kol melachah uvehemtecha. Don't do any מלאכה melachah and your animal.
אתה ולמה כתב רחמנא אתה ובהמתך? Atah velamah kasav rachamana atah uvehemtecha?
You and your animal. So you could have said exactly the same,
you together with your animal. But the גמרא Gemara says no it's
coming to tell you הוא ניהו דמחייב. hu nihu demichayev. At the
end of the day yes you can't let your animal do work
but אתה, atah, you are of a different status than your animal.
When you transgress when you do it then you transgress and you
get you know מיתה. misah. בהמה לא מחייב. Beheimah lo mechayev. For
your animal you don't even not only you not get מיתה misah
that's a completely different category you're not going to get מלקות. malkos.
So this version says you know it's quite interesting that you have
two approaches that the prohibition of מחמר mechamer is ממש חילול שבת.
mamash chilul Shabbos. You know you're using your animal and that's as
if you're doing it. So we have ideas of don't tell a
non-Jew to do it, doing it through someone which is sort of
rabbinic. Here there's the possibility that when I'm directly manipulating my animal
it's like I did the חילול שבת chilul Shabbos and I would
get סקילה. skilah. That seems to be the idea. You could say
no it's סקילה skilah for a different thing. There are ל"ט מלאכות
lamed tes melachos and a prohibition of מחמר. mechamer. מחמר Mechamer is
also סקילה. skilah. But I would rather see it as broadening the
sense of what it means to do a מלאכה. melachah. And that's
two approaches. You know one says you don't bring a קרבן korban
but two approaches say that you get סקילה. skilah. In the end
we פסק pasken like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan which says no no
no it's completely different and therefore you know it's not חילול שבת
chilul Shabbos of doing a מלאכה. melachah. It's a לאו lav maybe
but not even a לאו lav that you get מלקות. malkos. Now
I do want by the way to say two things at both
extremes. As I said before to repeat the רמב"ן Ramban says there
are times when you are so involved you actually are considered doing
the מלאכה. melachah. He says again like if your animal is plowing
and you're holding on to the plow as it's plowing that's considered
like you're doing it with your animal. And at the other extreme
רמב"ם Rambam says that not only do you is it a לאו
lav and you don't get מלקות malkos which is what the גמרא
Gemara sounds like but the רמב"ם Rambam understands from the conclusion of
the גמרא Gemara that it's not even a לאו. lav. At least
that's the way there's a question if that's the position of the
רמב״ם, Rambam, but that's the way the רמב״ן Ramban understands the רמב״ם.
Rambam. So much that it's just the עשה. aseh. But in general
I would to repeat what I said before, there's usually an assumption
that there are two types of issues. There's a positive מצוה mitzvah
to ensure your animal rests, which is why, for example, I have
to make, you know, the whole פרק perek about במה בהמה יוצאה.
Bameh Behemah Yotzah. I can't I have to make sure that things
aren't on my animal before שבת Shabbos begins so it just doesn't
walk around on its own and have stuff on it. I'm not
involved. It just has stuff on its back and it's carrying it.
That's why I can't rent my animals to non-Jews. They're going to
use it on שבת. Shabbos. I have a positive obligation to ensure
it doesn't do it. But that's only my animals. Then there's another
issue, which is it doesn't matter whose animal it is, where I'm
directly doing the מלאכה melacha with the animal itself. That's לא תעשה
כל מלאכה. lo sa'aseh kol melacha. That's what we're talking about about
מחמר. mechamer. Yes, Josh? When רמב״ם Rambam lists the commandments, what does
he... yeah, he does not have a לאו lav for מחמר. mechamer.
He only includes the עשה. aseh. Right. So the question is, does
he still think that it's the לאו lav of לא תעשה מלאכה
lo sa'aseh melacha without the מלקות malkus or whatever? Anyway, that's a
question in the רמב״ם. Rambam. Okay, so now we move on to
that was very this was like the core גמרא Gemara about this
issue of אתה ובהמתך. ata u'vehemtecha. So now we go on to
the next discussion, which gets to, okay, you got the stuff to
a courtyard, and now we're not going to give any more allowances,
and now we have to worry about the מוקצה muktzah issue. So
what do you do? So it says you take off the stuff
that isn't מוקצה, muktzah, and you undo the bundles and all the
מוקצה muktzah stuff falls down. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says
about this. הגיע לחצר החיצונה. Higia l'chatzer hachitzonah. You came to the
outer courtyard of the city where it would be protected. So the
allowances stop. אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Huna. Said רב הונא. Rav
Huna. היתה בהמתו טעונה כלי זכוכית. Haysah behemto te'unah klei zechuchis. Let's
say you had glass vessels on it. So if you undo your
things and falls down and it's going to break, what do you
do? מביא כסתות ומניח תחתיה. Mevi kesasos u'maniach tachteha. And so you
bring pillows and מתיר החבלים matir hachavalim then you undo the the
ropes והשקין נופלין v'hasakin noflin and the sacks fall and the and
the glass doesn't break. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute.
והא תנן נוטלין כלי לפני השבת. V'ha tnan notlin kli lifnei haShabbos.
But we had said in the משנה mishna and you could anyway
assume that you can move the vessels that are not מוקצה. muktzah.
So who needs pillows? Glass vessels, they're not מוקצה. muktzah. Just take
them straight off the donkey. So the גמרא Gemara says no. כי
קאמר רב הונא בקרני דאומנא. Ki ka'amar Rav Huna bekarni de'umna. רב
הונא Rav Huna was talking about horns of a bloodletter. You know,
apparently that they would like a like a funnel-shaped type of a
thing that after presumably they would cut in and open the vein,
you know, they would put this thing, this like tube in or
whatever and the blood would come out. I don't know exactly. Anyway,
that was made out of glass and that is something that is
מוקצה. muktzah. רש״י Rashi says it's disgusting, you know, obviously you're not
going to use that. Maybe it's also a type of a כלי
אומנות, kli umanus, so which makes it... so anyway that is מוקצה
muktzah and those are the things you don't want to break. So
how do you deal with this? You can't directly handle them, you
put the pillows underneath them. דלא חזי ליה. D'lo chazi leh. It's
not fit for him. So okay, so that's the explanation. Now the
גמרא Gemara has a question. One minute. והא קמבטל כלי מהיכנו. V'ha
kamvatel kli meheichano. One minute, it says, you are, you know, sort
of negating a vessel from its use. Because now you're going to
have a pillow that's going to have this מוקצה muktzah item on
it. Okay, and you're not going to be able to use the
pillow. So you're not on שבת Shabbos allowed to do something that
makes a כלי kli not usable. Okay, could be it's like סותר
soter maybe, destroying, whatever the reason is, the rabbis did not allow
you to do something that makes a כלי kli not usable. Now,
somebody will ask me, but what do you mean? Even if there
is a מוקצה muktzah item on it, didn't we have a whole
פרק perek about, you know, moving the bed out from underneath the
money that's on it and so on? So, it's not a בסיס
basis and you just move the pillow. Yeah, but what's going to
happen if you move the pillow? The glass will break. It'll fall
down and break. So it's not because of the מוקצה muktzah problem,
but now you can't move the pillow because your the glass is
going to break. So you have made the pillow unusable. So the
גמרא Gemara says oh, there there are solutions to that. So the
גמרא Gemara says בשליפי זוטרי. bishlifi zutri. With small sacks. Which it
the way רש״י Rashi says what it means is small sacks is
is that basically you can remove the pillow and it's not heavy,
it's not weighing down the pillow so much that you can't move
the pillow. You can move the pillow, you move the pillow and
it falls let's say to another pillow and you slowly get it
to go closer and closer to the ground, so finally when you
pull out the final pillow, it's very close to the ground and
it's not going to break. But basically, yeah, there are ways of
doing it so that you can still use the pillow and pull
it out from under and the glass won't break. So the גמרא
Gemara says מיתיבי. Meisivei. Okay, let me ask on this. היתה בהמתו
טעונה תבל. Haysah behemto te'unah tevel. We have a ברייתא. beraisa. If
your בהמה behema was carrying תבל, tevel, untithed grain, which is מוקצה.
muktzah. ואששיות. V'ashashiyos. Now אששיות, ashashiyos, אשיש ashish often means glass lanterns,
but we'll see the גמרא Gemara is going to say that it
means chunks of glass actually. Okay, מתיר את החבלים, matir es hachavalim,
you undo the ropes והשקין נופלין v'hasakin noflin and the and the
sacks fall ואף על פי שמשתברין v'af al pi shemishtabrin even though
it's going to break. So here presumably if it's a chunk of
glass, it's מוקצה. muktzah. You know, maybe it's raw materials to use
for a window or something, but it's מוקצה, muktzah, so you can't
directly handle it and it doesn't give the pillow solution. Presumably because
of the problem of קמבטל כלי מהיכנו. kamvatel kli meheichano. Now of
course you could have... Instead of it's such a big chunk that
you really would stop the pillow from being usable, you know you
could be if that's the issue, but let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. התם בכולסיא, Hatam bechulsya, that's talking about a like a
chunk of glass, not a lantern. Why does that make it any
better? רש"י Rashi says because you can still use even after it
breaks you can use the pieces. Now I don't get it, what
are you going to use tiny little parts pieces for but I
was thinking that maybe רש"י Rashi maybe melt them down, I was
thinking that maybe you could also use them if you're doing mosaic
with it. You know, if it's colored glass, right, then you could
use them for mosaic. But anyway, okay, so somehow therefore it's not
a real loss. So the גמרא Gemara says דיקא נמי dika nami
and that can be inferred by close reading דקתני דומיא דטבלא, dekani
dumya detavla, like טבלא. tavla. מה טבלא דלא חזיא ליה, ma tavla
delo chazi lei, the same way טבלא tavla something like completely unusable,
אף הכא נמי לא חזיא ליה, af hacha nami lo chazi lei,
here too it's unusable, so it makes sense that we're talking about
a big chunk of glass, not maybe let's say a lantern which
would be the the story. So the גמרא Gemara says okay that's
true, מאי אף על פי שמשתברין mai af al pi shemishtabrin then
what's the meaning even though they break, if there's not a problem,
you're not concerned about it breaking? No, מהו דתימא ma d'teima אימא
אית ליה להפסד מועט נמי aima itloah lehefsed muat nami חשישו chashushu
even though it's not a huge loss it's a small loss. What's
the small loss? So if you say like Charlie, the small loss
is now you're going to have to remelt it or whatever. If
you say רש"י Rashi says the small loss is the little shards.
Even if you want to use the broken pieces, I really do
think it's talking about like a mosaic, but obviously it breaks into
usable pieces and unusable pieces and there is going to be some
loss. Okay, so קא משמע לן kamashma lan that we are not
concerned with that. So now according to the גמרא Gemara basically what
you can you cannot for concern of מבטל כלי מהיכנו, mevatel kli
meheichano, they what do you call it? For a concern of מבטל
כלי מהיכנו mevatel kli meheichano you would not be allowed to put
the pillow under to stop the glass from breaking. And the reason
the גמרא Gemara says that you could do it in the first
scenario was because there would be a way to take the pillow
out from underneath. Okay and so that is but if there wasn't
a way to take the pillow out from underneath or if it
was only a minor loss you know then we wouldn't allow it.
Okay, תניא tanya we taught in a ברייתא Braitah רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי אומר Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai omer היתה בהמתו טעונה שליף של
תבואה, hayta behemto teuna shalif shel tvua, if your animal was carrying
a sack of grain, מניח ראשו תחתיה ומסלקה לצד אחר והוא נופל
מאליה. mianiach rosho tachteiha mesalko letzad acher vehu nofel me'elav. Okay then
you put your head like underneath the sack of grain and like
you move it with your body and it falls onto the other
side of the animal then it falls off. Now the question is
why did you need to do all of that right? Why don't
you just directly remove it? So it could be that we're talking
again about like טבל. tevel. If it's טבל tevel how do you
move טבל tevel and so on. So he says like with מוקצה
muktzah you can move it like we talked about טלטול בגוף tiltul
beguf when you're using your body and not your hands and that's
not a מוקצה muktzah problem. So here's another solution rather than undoing
the ropes and letting it fall and maybe making a mess. Okay,
you know maybe something bad will happen, maybe there's a different solution.
We'll see another concern that there might have been that there might
be also with untying stuff from the animal. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this חמורו של רבן גמליאל, chamoro shel Rabban Gamliel, רבן
גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel donkey היתה טעונה דבש hayta teuna dvash was carrying
honey. ולא רצה לפורקה עד מוצאי שבת v'lo ratza le'porka ad motzai
Shabbat and he didn't want to undo it until שבת Shabbat was
over because you undo it the barrel of honey falls down you
ruin all this honey quite expensive. So למוצאי שבת מתה lemotzai Shabbat
meita and then by the time שבת Shabbat was over the donkey
had died because it had this weight on it that it was
not right. So the גמרא Gemara obviously you know seems to be
critical of this choice and we're going to see that it's going
to turn into a discussion of צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim.
Okay so but so he was being so פרום frum he didn't
want to do it and look what the consequence was the animal
died. So the גמרא Gemara says והאנן תנן, v'anan tnan, so the
גמרא Gemara says I don't even understand what was bothering him. We
teach נוטלו הכלים הניטלין, notlo hakelim hanitlin, you can take off the
non-מוקצה muktzah items. Honey isn't מוקצה. muktzah. גמרא Gemara says כשהקדיש. k'shehikdish.
No it spoiled. It's funny that the word for honey spoiling is
the word of דבש הקדיש. dvash hikdish. It sounded like it became
honey, no but anyway it spoiled. So it spoiled it is מוקצה.
muktzah. So the גמרא Gemara says הקדיש hikdish it spoiled? למאי חזי?
l'mai chazi? So then why is he even bothering with it? What
do you use spoiled honey for? לכתיתא דגמלי. likitita d'gamlei. You rub
it into the sores of camels. So it would have some medicinal
use but it would not be used on שבת. Shabbat. So he
didn't want to he didn't want to do it because it was
מוקצה. muktzah. Okay but we see what the consequence was. So the
גמרא Gemara says I don't get it, there were other options. ויתיר
חבלים ויפלו שקים? v'yatir chavalim v'yiplu sakim? Why not just undo it
and let the sacks fall? So and so it says מצרו זיקי,
mitzru ziki, no because the barrels will break and maybe then the
honey will spill. ויביא כר וכסת ויניח תחתיהם? v'yavi kar v'ksata v'yanach
tachteihem? Okay so do the pillow trick. Alright so it says מיתנפי,
mitanfi, no because they'll get honey on them these pillows, דקא מבטל
כלי מהיכנו d'kama vatel kli meheichano and they won't be usable anymore
right? Maybe you'll say it's usable because you pull the pillow and
the barrel falls down but no the pillow gets soiled so you're
making the pillow unusable so that wasn't the solution. We didn't allow
it when you were מבטל כלי מהיכנו. mevatel kli meheichano. So now
the Gemara says באיכא צער בעלי חיים. b'ika tza'ar ba'alei chayim. Okay,
but the animal is suffering. So even though there's a rabbinic problem,
you override rabbinic concerns to alleviate the suffering of animals and actually
a classic example of that is that the animal is down the
well and you lower down pillows to the animal so it can
be on them and not be in pain sort of in the
water in the well. And even though you're מבטל כלי מהיכנו, mevatel
kli meheichano, you make the pillow unusable, you're allowed to do it
for צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. So what was the big
deal? Get some pillows! So what, מבטל כלי, mevatel kli, there's an
animal suffering here. So the Gemara says קסבר, kasavar, he is of
the opinion צער בעלי חיים דרבנן, tza'ar ba'alei chayim derabbanan, that it's
not a biblical concern, animal suffering, it's only a rabbinic concern and
therefore it would not override other rabbinic concerns. So this by the
way is why the issue whether צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim
is biblical or rabbinic really has immediate halakhic implication and this is
how the Gemara uses it. Can, does צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei
chayim override rabbinic prohibitions? And the answer is yes if it's biblical,
no if it's rabbinic. If it's rabbinic, it's an equal battle, two
rabbinic things against one another. If it's biblical, it has greater weight.
And we actually rule that it is biblical. By the way, that's
how we deal with the whole issue about milking cows on Shabbos
because if you have a dairy, they've got to be milked every
day and also you lose your business. So I won't talk about
the business aspect of it and can you benefit from it, but
because they are suffering when they're not being milked, you're allowed to
do דרבננס derabbanans to milk them on Shabbos. Have a non-Jew do
it, do it through setting them up to some automatic mechanical contraption
before and then it'll turn on and it'll work after it's already
hooked up. Various things that they do in Israel because צער בעלי
חיים דאורייתא tza'ar ba'alei chayim d'oraisa we rule and does override. So
yes, it's the Gemara's pointing out sort of the tragedy that ensued,
but is speaking about how he because of his positions on צער
בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim he let it happen. I don't know
if the upshot is supposed to be that the Gemara feels, 'Oh,
okay, then we're okay with it,' or in the end, there's still
some sense here that you should have figured out some way to
have dealt with the problem. Okay, so now the Gemara goes אביי
אשכחיה לרבה, Abaye ashkechei l'Rabba, Abaye found Rabba, his rebbe, דקמשפשף ליה
לבריה אגב דחמרא, d'kameshafshaf lei l'brei agav d'chamra, he was rubbing his
son on the side of a donkey. Maybe whatever he was doing,
he was having rubbing, scratching his son's back or just having some
fun with his kid. But the concern here is going to be,
we'll get back to our case about undoing the ropes, but here
the concern is going to be that you're not allowed to ride
on a donkey and you're not allowed to climb a tree on
Shabbat. And that becomes abstracted to: you can't use an animal and
you can't use a tree on Shabbat. So the question is going
to be what does it mean which part of the animal and
which part of the tree can't I use? The top of the
animal and the top of the tree, or does it mean even
the sides? And so here the concern was, aren't you using this
animal? And this is going to be an important discussion about using
the sides of a tree. I'll just tell you a practical example.
Can you lie in a hammock on Shabbat that is hooked up
to a tree? Are you using the side of a tree? Okay,
so we will have an answer to that by the time we
finish this discussion. Let's take a look. Gemara says like this: דקמשפשף
ליה לבריה אגב דחמרא d'kameshafshaf lei l'brei agav d'chamra was rubbing his
son on the side of a donkey. אמר ליה קמשתמש מר בבעלי
חיים, amar lei kameshtamesh mar b'ba'alei chayim, is the master using animals
on Shabbos? אמר ליה צדדים הם, amar lei tzedadim heim, it's the
side of the animal, וצדדים לא גזרו בהו רבנן, v'tzedadim lo gazru
b'hu rabbanan, and the sides weren't decreed by the Rabbis. It says
don't ride, don't use, means don't use the top, the same place
you would ride, it doesn't mean the side. מנא תימרא, mena teimra,
where do you get this idea from? דתנן, d'tnan, because it says,
מתיר החבלים והשקים נופלים, matir hachavalim v'hasakim noflim, you undo the ropes
and the sacks fall. מאי לאו דחבר גבאלקי, mai lav d'chavar gavalaki,
whatever that is, דהוו להו צדדים. d'havu lehu tzedadim. Isn't it talking
about that the sacks are combined with this gavalaki hookup? The way
Rashi seems to explain it, it's essentially like let's say saddlebags on
the side of the donkey. And if I have to undo, I
have to somehow undo it by dealing with the bags on both
sides at the same time, which means as I'm undoing the ropes,
I'm leaning on the donkey to get to the other side. So
I'm using the donkey because I'm leaning on it, it's helping support
my weight. So look, you're allowed to undo the ropes and it
falls down. Obviously, you're going to be leaning on the donkey in
that process. So you're using the side of the donkey, וצדדים לא
גזרו בהו רבנן, v'tzedadim lo gazru b'hu rabbanan, so you see the
Rabbis didn't make that decree by the side. לא דחבר אגאלבקי lo
d'chavar agalvaki דלא הוו צדדים, d'lo havu tzedadim, no, with a different
type of a thing where you're not using the sides. The way
Rashi explains it is that you more, there's more like they're more
combined by some type of a by, they're on both sides, but
they're combined by a loop in the middle and all you have
to do is like pull out the peg and they fall down.
So therefore, yeah, I know, I know. But, and therefore there's a
way you can undo it without actually having to lean on the
side. אינמי בלחטא, einami b'lachta, or with a rope, some type of
a rope that they're suspended from again that you can undo the
rope without and they're not combined, both sides are not combined to
one another and there's a way to free them without leaning on
the donkey. Okay. איתיביה, eiseivei, let me ask you. Now we have
a sukkah case. שתים בידי אדם, shtayim b'yedei adam, if you have
two walls of the sukkah made by a person, like man-made walls,
ואחת באילן, v'achas b'ilan, and one wall is a tree. כשרה, kesherah,
it's a כשרה סוכה kesherah sukkah ואין עולין לה ביום טוב. ve'ein
olin lah beyom tov. You can't go into it on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. The only reason it says עולין, olin, you would have
thought עולין olin meant like it's a treehouse going up the tree,
but it doesn't seem that's the case. And רש"י Rashi says that
עולין olin means because they would standard make their סוכות sukkahs on
the roof. So whenever it talks about going into the סוכה, sukkah,
it talks about you're עולין olin into the סוכה. sukkah. And when
it talks about leaving the סוכה, sukkah, it says you're יורד yored
into the house. Okay, so you can't go into a סוכה sukkah
on יום טוב Yom Tov if one of the walls... you can
go on חול המועד Chol HaMoed but not on יום טוב Yom
Tov if one of the walls is made by a tree. Now,
what's the scenario? מאי לאו mai lav is it not talking about
דחק ביה באילן dechakei be'ilan that basically this is let's say the
trunk of the tree, okay? And what I do is here, I
put a, you know, I put some type of a beam, a
rafter as it were, like into the trunk of the tree, you
know, to suspend it. And then I use that to help support
the סכך. schach. Okay, so it's assuming... you could have assumed that
the סכך schach is directly on the tree, but then it would
have to be like cut off and shaved or whatever. So this
is part of a whole trunk. How am I going to use
it as a wall? Because I'm going to use it because maybe
I'll attach let's say a shelf to that thing and that'll help
support the סכך. schach. So what's that mean? I'm using the side
of the tree, not the top of the tree, and that's why
I can't go into it on שבת. Shabbos. Now the question is,
what do you mean use it? You're just sitting under the סכך.
schach. So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say they would store
let's say some of their various vessels, like maybe dishes and pots
and pans on the סכך, schach, on top of the סכך. schach.
So you want... you would take the stuff off the סכך schach
and the סכך schach is supported by the shelf attached to the
side of a tree. Therefore you would be using the tree. So
you see the גמרא Gemara assumes that's the scenario. So you see
that there's a problem using the side of a tree. So it
says מאי לאו mai lav דחק ביה באילן dechakei be'ilan you carved
into the tree, you let's say and inserted a shelf דהוה ליה
משתמש dehavei leh mishtamesh now you're using the side and then you're
going to use the סכך schach not just sit under it but
actually, you know, pick stuff off the סכך schach and therefore use
the side of the tree. ומשתמש אסור umishtamesh assur and you see
the sides are forbidden. גמרא Gemara says לא דכפייה לאילן ואנח סכך
עילויה. lo dechafyei le'ilan ve'anach schach iluyei. No, if you've got this
tall big tree, well, maybe you'll have to give a better example.
If you've got this tall big tree, how do you use it?
Because you have let's say two trees and you bend over their
branches, the top of them and their branches, and you know, and
that's how you sort of make this into a wall. So and
then when you put something on it, you actually put it on
top of the like the branches and the leaves and not on
the side and not on the trunk. So yes, you've constructed it
in a way that you're using the top of the tree, not
the trunk, and therefore it is going to be a problem of
using the tree. But if it was the side, the trunk, it
would not be a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
אי הכי ei hachi if that's true, אימא סיפא eima seifa let's
look at the end. שלוש בידי אדם ואחת באילן shalosh bidei adam
ve'achat be'ilan if three of the walls are man-made and one is
a tree כשרה kesherah not only is it כשרה kesherah obviously, ועולין
לה ביום טוב ve'olin lah beyom tov you can use it on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So גמרא Gemara says, I don't get it.
וכי דכפייה לאילן vechi dechafyei le'ilan but if you bent over the
trees, you know, and you're using the tops as one of as
like a as a wall and as a roof as a wall,
אמאי עולין לה ביום טוב amai olin lah beyom tov still why
is it okay? They're supporting the סכך schach and you're using the
סכך. schach. So and you, you know, and if you're using the
סכך schach you're using the tree. Who cares if it's a fourth
wall? You're still using the tree. So גמרא Gemara says okay, but
that's a problem however you explain this. ואלא מאי ve'ela mai משתמש
אסור mishtamesh assur so how do you want to explain it? That
you're using the trunk of the tree and that's the problem. סוף
סוף sof sof אמאי עולין לה ביום טוב amai olin lah beyom
tov you still don't have... you still have to explain why it's
not a problem when it's the fourth wall. Right? Whatever the problem
is, either using the top of the tree or side of the
tree, why does that problem go away when it's the fourth wall
if that tree is still supporting the סכך schach and you're using
therefore the סכך schach and using the tree. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא התם בגוזא דפרסכנא. ela hatam beguza deparsachna. There it's a
case of גוזא דפרסכנא. guza deparsachna. רש"י Rashi basically says it's a
type of a tree, pine tree essentially where you have branches coming
out all along the sides. So essentially you don't need to bind
it at all, it just naturally forms a wall based on, you
know, the configuration of the branches. דאילן גופיה דופן בעלמא הוא דשוייה.
de'ilan gufey dophan be'alma hu deshavyei. And therefore you're using it as
a wall but not as a supporting wall. Meaning רש"י Rashi says
the idea that it was a pine tree is really irrelevant. The
basic answer is that in this case the סכך schach is supported
by the three man-made walls. This fourth one is just like a
curtain. It's not, you know, it's not supporting any weight. And since
it's not supporting any weight, when you're using the סכך schach you're
not using the fourth wall. Okay? So the basic point is that
if the סכך schach is supported on the tree, you can't use
the סכך schach because you're using the tree. If the tree is
an extra fourth wall not supporting it, not a problem. What part
of the tree are you using? Is it supported on the top
of the tree or on the side of the tree? That is
not clear. That's the question of whether there's an issue with the
trunk or just with the top. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara
goes. דיקא נמי דקתני זה הכלל. dayka nami dektani zeh haklal. This
idea that in this case it's okay because the fourth wall is
not really doing anything is inferred from the end of that משנה
mishnah because it says זה הכלל zeh haklal this is the rule
כל ש. kol she. If you would remove the tree and the
סוכה Sukkah would still stand, עולין לו ביום טוב, olin lo be-Yom
Tov, you can use it because then the tree isn't supporting the
סכך, s'chach, so you can use it even on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. שמע מינה. Shma mina. Oh, that's a good explanation of the
fourth wall, but the piece about the third wall and what way
were you using the tree, that's not clear from the משנה. Mishna.
לימא כתנאי. Leima ketannai. Maybe this connects to a debate of תנאי.
Tannai. That we say what? אין עולים. Ein olim. לימא כתנאי. Leima
ketannai. אין עולים לביום טוב. Ein olim lo be-Yom Tov. You don't
go up into a סוכה Sukkah with this tree as a wall
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, like we said. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר משום רבי מאיר עולים לביום טוב. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer
mishum Rabbi Meir olin lo be-Yom Tov. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says
in the name of Rabbi Meir you can use it. So why
can you use it? מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי. Mai lav be-ha kamiflagi.
Maybe this is exactly the debate, that it's being supported by the
trunk of the tree, the סכך, s'chach, and מר סבר צדדים אסורים,
mar savar tzedadim asurim, one says that's not acceptable to use the
side of a tree, ומר סבר מותרים, umar savar mutarim, and the
other says that it is. Maybe this is exactly what they're debating.
So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, לא, lo, no, that is not the
debate. דכולי עלמא צדדים אסורים, dekuli alma tzedadim asurim, everybody can assume
that, probably can say that the sides are forbidden. והכא בצדי צדדים
קמיפלגי. vehacha be-tziddei tzedadim kamiflagi. What if it's about the side of
a side? I'll read it and then I'll explain it. מר סבר
צדי צדדים אסורים, mar savar tziddei tzedadim asurim, one says it's forbidden,
ומר סבר צדי צדדים מותרים, umar savar tziddei tzedadim mutarim, it's permissible.
Which means what? If you were actually the סכך s'chach were actually
to be inserted into the side of the tree, then you would
be using the side of the tree. You're using the סכך, s'chach,
you're using the side of the tree. But the סכך s'chach isn't
inserted into the side of the tree. The סכך s'chach rests on
a shelf and the shelf is inserted in the side of the
tree. So when you use the סכך, s'chach, it's only directly making
use of the shelf, and the use of the side of the
tree is one degree removed. That he said would be is the
debate about whether that would be okay. This is going to be
very relevant for the hammock situation because if I tie my hammock
rope directly on the tree, the trunk, that's צדדים. tzedadim. If I
put in a peg and tie it around the peg, then that's
צדי צדדים, tziddei tzedadim, because I'm only directly using the peg and
only indirectly using the trunk of the tree. You say what do
you say? That's actually how we פסקן pasken by the way, not
to give away the end. Yes. So what about if the net
is attached to the rope which is attached to the tree? Yeah,
but even without saying that, it's okay. Oh, you mean if it's
directly the rope to the tree? That's an interesting question. Maybe if
the rope was a freestanding rope, you know what I mean? But
if the rope is a part of the net, then I don't
think you could make that argument and that's the way they're normally
made. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like, so that's how אביי
Abaye says. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, I don't buy
that. מאן דאסר בצדדים, man de-asar be-tzedadim, if you say the trunk
is forbidden, אסר נמי בצדי צדדים, asar nami be-tziddei tzedadim, then things
attached to the trunk are forbidden. ומאן דשרי בצדי צדדים, uman de-shari
be-tziddei tzedadim, and if things attached to the trunk are allowed, like
the peg in the side of the tree or the wall, the
shelf, שרי נמי בצדדים, shari nami be-tzedadim, then also the trunk itself.
I don't believe that there should be a difference. Okay. איתיביה רמי
בר חמא לרבא. Eitivei Rami bar Chama le-Rava. רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama asked against רבא Rava who denied a difference between צדדים
tzedadim and צדי צדדים. tziddei tzedadim. Let's read a little bit further.
נעץ יתד. Na'atz yated. We have a few minutes, let's make sure
we finish, go to the משנה. Mishna. נעץ יתד. Na'atz yated. I
already gave you the ending away anyway. נעץ יתד באילן. Na'atz yated
be-ilan. So here exactly, almost exactly, is the scenario similar to the
hammock. You put a peg in a tree, ותלה בה כלכלה, ve-talah
bah kalkalah, and you put a basket, you hung a basket from
it. Can you use the basket hanging on the peg in the
trunk of a tree? So אם למעלה מעשרה טפחים, im le-ma'alah me-asarah
tefachim, and this, the story is you have food in the basket
and that was supposed to serve as your עירוב eiruv to allow
you to walk outside of the תחום. techum. Now, it's only a
good עירוב eiruv if you could access the food on שבת Shabbat
or on בין השמשות. bein ha-shmashot. So are you allowed to get
the food from this basket or are you in the same place
as the food? So למעלה מעשרה טפחים, le-ma'alah me-asarah tefachim, if it's
higher than ten טפחים, tefachim, אין עירובו עירוב, ein eiruvo eiruv, it
doesn't count because your feet are in רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim and
the food is higher than ten טפחים tefachim which is outside of
רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. למטה מעשרה טפחים, le-mattan me-asarah tefachim, if it's
within ten טפחים, tefachim, עירובו עירוב, eiruvo eiruv, it's good. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so you, so he says okay, but how about
using the side of the tree? Okay. So טעמא, ta'ama, so it
sounds like the reason it's okay to get the basket, use the
food in the basket, דנעץ יתד באילן, de-na'atz yated be-ilan, because you've
got a peg in the side of the tree. הא לאו נעץ,
ha lav na'atz, if you didn't have the peg and the basket
was directly hanging on the tree, אפילו למטה מעשרה טפחים, afilu le-mattan
me-asarah tefachim, even below ten טפחים, tefachim, אין עירובו עירוב, ein eiruvo
eiruv, presumably it would not be good because then you'd be using
the tree. דהא הכא דקתני בצדדים. de-ha hacha de-katani be-tzedadim. So again,
because he gave the scenario, he pointed out the peg, it suggests
that without the peg it's forbidden, וקתני בצדי צדדים. ve-katani be-tziddei tzedadim.
So therefore the peg makes the difference. Without the peg it's the
side of the tree, it's a problem. With the peg it's something
attached to the tree and it's okay. So it's implicit by the
fact that it describes and it goes out of its way to
describe the scenario with the peg. So אמר רב פפה, amar Rav
Papa, no, there's a different way that can make a difference. הכא
בכלכלה דחוקה עסקינן. hacha be-kalkalah de-chukah askinan. Maybe this תנא Tanna holds
that there's not a problem even using the side of the tree,
but there's an issue which is is that it is very tightly,
if you were to attach it directly, I'm sorry, it's got a
very narrow opening, so if it were directly attached to the tree,
דבהדי דשקיל ליה, d'bahadi d'shakil lei, you have to stick your hand
in and get the food out, right, with a tight opening. What's
that going to do? דשקיל ליה אתי לאטויי אילנא, d'shakil lei ati
l'atuyei ilana, it would cause the tree to move. So the problem
here is that basically we could assume that the side of the
tree would totally be okay. But it's a scenario where if it's
tightly attached to the tree, as you're going for the food, it's
going to cause the tree to shake and that'll be moving the
top of the tree which is the problem, which is considered like
using it. But if it's on a peg, then you can, then
it won't, the tree won't shake and therefore it'll be okay. באילנא
וקמשתמש באילנא גופיה, b'ilana v'kamishtamesh b'ilana gufei, you'll move the tree and
you'll be using the tree itself. Of course, it's pretty funny that
that's called using the tree. Who needs that? But maybe because it's
helping serve my function, even though I don't really care that it's
shaking, somehow that is a problem. Anyway, so we have this debate
whether to distinguish between the side of the tree and something attached
to the side of the tree. והלכתא, V'hilchasa, the halacha is: צדדין
אסורין, tzdadin asurin, you cannot use the trunk of the tree; צדי
צדדין, tzidei tzdadin, things that are attached to the trunk, מותרין, mutarin,
you can use. And now the Gemara is going to give, apply
this למעשה. l'maiseh. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, השתא דאמרת צדדין
אסורין, hashta d'amart tzdadin asurin, now that you're telling me I can't
directly use the side of the tree, האי דרגא דמדלא, hai darga
d'madla, this type of basically a ladder that is used for going
up to like, Rashi says like a crow's nest, לא לינחיה אינש
אדיקלא, lo linchei inash a'dikla, don't put it against a palm tree,
דהוה ליה צדדין, d'havei lei tzdadin, because then the ladder is being
supported by the trunk and you're using the trunk of the tree.
Because the ladder is being directly supported by the trunk. אלא, Ella,
how do you solve it? לינחיה אגוזא לבר מדיקלא, linchei a'guza l'var
midikla, so you should put, you should put basically Rashi says I
think he says it's a peg, yeah, you should put a peg
that sticks out from the side of the tree. וכי סליק, V'chi
salik, and as you're going up, לא לינח כרעיה אגוזא, lo linach
krei a'guza, don't make sure not to rest your leg on the
peg which is out of the tree, because that's a... אלא לינתח
אקנים, ella lintach a'kanim, but put it on the, but put it
on actually the rungs of the ladder. So basically if you are,
right, if you're directly using the peg, you know, so then it
is that, then that's like you're using the side of the tree.
If the ladder is resting on the peg and you're using the
ladder, or if the basket is hanging from the peg, or your
hammock is hanging from the peg and you're in your hammock, right,
then you're okay. So you can use something that is supported by
something attached to the tree, but you cannot use something that is
directly attached... to use the peg would be using the side of
the tree. To use the hammock or the ladder that is resting
on the peg, that's צדי צדדין, tzidei tzdadin, that's okay, and that
actually is the way we פוסקן, pasken, so everybody can go use
their hammocks, just make sure they have a nail and not directly
tied. I must have had...